<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Recollection - javascript</title><link href="https://recollection.saaj.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://recollection.saaj.me/tag/javascript.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://recollection.saaj.me/</id><updated>2014-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Qooxdoo “next” and targeting website development</title><link href="https://recollection.saaj.me/article/qooxdoo-next-and-targeting-website-development.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2014-12-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>saaj</name></author><id>tag:recollection.saaj.me,2014-12-08:/article/qooxdoo-next-and-targeting-website-development.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Initially, this post was meant to be an open letter to Martin Wittemann, an urge to do not break the only
robust and consistent JavaScript development environment, in sense of bug #8618 [1]. How robust and
consistent? Most importantly it is&amp;nbsp;about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code structure: modern feature-rich object model with properties, events, interfaces, mixins and more,
namespace tree,&amp;nbsp;data-binding,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependency management: automatic and transparent dependency resolution, component&amp;nbsp;packaging,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment: code optimisation, single- and multi-part&amp;nbsp;builds,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard library: i18n, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CLDR&lt;/span&gt;, high level &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BOM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;, normalised events, normalised ECMAScript, test
infrastructure, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; documentation, feature&amp;nbsp;detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this comes out-of-the-box, builds layer on layer, is seamlessly integrated and handed to an end developer
on a silver platter. The codebase is one of the best quality I have ever seen. It is readable,
comprehensible, possible to extend, and is a huge a knowledge resource per se. And note, I am talking about
tools and environment, not &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;. Like former Qooxdoo developer, Fabian Jakobs, stated in one of his
presentations [2]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Don’t just look at the widgets, look at the development tools as well.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, as was recently stated in &lt;em&gt;Website fundamentals: next challenges&lt;/em&gt; [3], the “next” (branch and then a
separate repo [4]; later referenced Next) turned out to be a experimental website-oriented fork of Qooxdoo,
which doesn’t mean to be merged back to Qooxdoo. At least any time soon. Panic is soothed, impending doom
doesn’t overhang the good times. It’s time to dissect and&amp;nbsp;discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Initially, this post was meant to be an open letter to Martin Wittemann, an urge to do not break the only
robust and consistent JavaScript development environment, in sense of bug #8618 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id22" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. How robust and
consistent? Most importantly it is&amp;nbsp;about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code structure: modern feature-rich object model with properties, events, interfaces, mixins and more,
namespace tree,&amp;nbsp;data-binding,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dependency management: automatic and transparent dependency resolution, component&amp;nbsp;packaging,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment: code optimisation, single- and multi-part&amp;nbsp;builds,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Standard library: i18n, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CLDR&lt;/span&gt;, high level &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BOM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;, normalised events, normalised ECMAScript, test
infrastructure, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; documentation, feature&amp;nbsp;detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this comes out-of-the-box, builds layer on layer, is seamlessly integrated and handed to an end developer
on a silver platter. The codebase is one of the best quality I have ever seen. It is readable,
comprehensible, possible to extend, and is a huge a knowledge resource per se. And note, I am talking about
tools and environment, not &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;. Like former Qooxdoo developer, Fabian Jakobs, stated in one of his
presentations &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id23" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Don’t just look at the widgets, look at the development tools as well.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, as was recently stated in &lt;em&gt;Website fundamentals: next challenges&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id24" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, the “next” (branch and then a
separate repo &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id25" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;; later referenced Next) turned out to be a experimental website-oriented fork of Qooxdoo,
which doesn’t mean to be merged back to Qooxdoo. At least any time soon. Panic is soothed, impending doom
doesn’t overhang the good times. It’s time to dissect and&amp;nbsp;discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="section" id="the-bug-report"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The bug&amp;nbsp;report&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was meant to break? The bug report mandated to rewrite Qooxdoo test infrastructure with callback
spaghetti of mocha.js. Callback spaghetti?! When most code structure is a callback in callback in callback
and so on, with the state expressed in free closure variables spanning across nesting levels, it is a
callback spaghetti. And for average JavaScript code out there this structure practice is very common, which
is nothing good though, but for Qooxdoo it might have been an awful decision, replacing clean,
object-oriented code with that. But since Next is not Qooxdoo it may depend on some&amp;nbsp;factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the report Martin&amp;nbsp;told:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
There has been some hard decisions for me to take lately but I&amp;#8217;m still convinced that not trying to be
the expert for everything gives us the opportunity to focus on our strengths.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And listed some features that supposedly impressed&amp;nbsp;him:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pretty&amp;nbsp;printing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scaffolding over to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XML&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;handling,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Levenshtein distance&amp;nbsp;calculation,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GUI&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;toolkits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First is simple, second is needed only for recorded tests (e.g. Selenium), third is already there with
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.util.EditDistance&lt;/tt&gt;. And forth is quite a thing Qooxdoo was made for. So these features are kind of
false&amp;nbsp;argument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;mocha.js&lt;/tt&gt; is 5k &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SLOC&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.dev.unit&lt;/tt&gt; is 4.4k &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SLOC&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;testrunner&lt;/tt&gt; is 3.9k &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SLOC&lt;/span&gt;. Including these
numbers and taking into account more expressive Qooxdoo code, either Martin is trading more for less, or it
is just an expensive&amp;nbsp;experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway framework consistency is absolutely a strength. Test code is a canonical source of thruth about an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt;.
Test code is required for maintaining a complex application (which most websites are not though). And test
infrastructure should not be compared to a disposal widget like &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.ui.embed.HtmlArea&lt;/tt&gt; which wasn’t quality
in first place, required special knowledge to maintain, and most importantly it isn’t hard create a wrapper
for TinyMCE implementing &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.ui.form.IStringForm&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.ui.form.IForm&lt;/tt&gt;. Since that moment it is
transparent and seamlessly integrated. Making test code an alien in a framework, makes it seamful,
inconsistent, and what is worst can discourage developers from writing tests. Well, of course unless all the
rest code is the&amp;nbsp;spaghetti.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last note here is how framework consistency from language perspective changes in the course of recent time.
Qooxdoo &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;branch_3_0_x&lt;/tt&gt; roughly has nothing but Qooxdoo JavaScript code for a browser and Python code for
generator. Next has Qooxdoo JavaScript code and mocha.js callback spaghetti test code for a browser, CommonJS
code for generator that varies being object-oriented prototypal code, procedural code, and Qooxdoo
object-oriented code, which also doesn’t exclude some Python code still necessary for new generator to
function. So what’s clear, having hard time maintaining this is one of likely&amp;nbsp;outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="goals"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andreas Ecker wrote in the post &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id24" id="id5"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, that they
&lt;em&gt;have been looking into the challenges of a more lightweight,  website-oriented approach to web applications&lt;/em&gt;.
Sounds quite ambiguous and curious at the same time. Lightweight in byte size? Website-oriented in a
non-widget &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;? At the same time, it sounds as odd as arithmetic approach to differential equations. Then he&amp;nbsp;expanded:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Reasons are two-fold: primarily, we are involved in company-internal projects in that very domain.
Secondly, by touching core components of qooxdoo we can experiment with benefits of web technologies and
concepts available today.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First thing, considering 1&amp;amp;1’s “very domain”, is probably something like Amazon &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AWS&lt;/span&gt; management &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt;. A
web-application which spans multiple pages, where each page has some &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; from server and complementing
JavaScript code. So it may be looked at as a “website-oriented approach”. Second thing again points to an&amp;nbsp;experiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="qxweb"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;qxWeb&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Qooxdoo targets websites since 2.0 which was released in June 2012 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id26" id="id6"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Initially I was enthusiastic about
qxWeb, I thought it’ll be another virtue of the framework, and I still think the idea to target websites is
right as even at mid-scale they benefit from most of Qooxdoo non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; features. But the design and development
of qxWeb seems to me misguided and mostly pointless&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year after qxWeb release, the time I was looking at it from various angles, trying to find its strength and
way to integrate it in my flow to make it handle infrastructure task I used to handle with Qooxdoo in case of
web application, I submitted the bug report &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id27" id="id7"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; that proposes design that enables website development with
Qooxdoo (native application type &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id35" id="id8"&gt;[14]&lt;/a&gt;), points qxWeb shortcomings and its possible shortcut-purpose, and the
problems to be solved for normal operation. The biggest problem with qxWeb is that it wasn’t designed to be a
Qooxdoo thing, but rather be jQuery with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; done right. Long story told short: it’s not for writing an
application, it’s for scribbling ad hoc per page scripts. And I would prefer qxWeb over jQuery for writing
one-off script, but in general jQuery is de facto standard in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; patching and I don’t see any significant
niche for qxWeb as yet another &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; patcher plus this and that. Moreover even for shortcut-purpose in a
Qooxdoo application, qxWeb is still an alien, because it needs manual dependency declaration for its
“modules”. Qooxdoo way of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; patching was &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;qx.bom.Collection&lt;/tt&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id28" id="id9"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;, removed in version 3.0. I think it was
a&amp;nbsp;mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with Qooxdoo 3.5 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id29" id="id10"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;, there was an addition to qxWeb. Since then it supported low-level widgets.
Such widget expects certain &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; structure and classes, which later is animated on widget instance
construction. Basically, qxWeb started to mimic jQueryUI as well, not just jQuery. Not that I want to say
it’s useless, but rather it’s reinvention of the wheel, reimplementation of a task that was already
implemented long ago, and all who wanted such functionality already have it at hand. What’s worse the
reimplementation is being done with outdated technology. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; binding, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MVVM&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id30" id="id11"&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt;, libraries emerged in
2009-2010, and at the moment of Qooxdoo 3.5 release, late 2013, were a commodity, as well as understanding
that a lot of manual &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; patching is a chore, that can be automated with a view model. Bug #8101 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id31" id="id12"&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt; lead
me to working KnockoutJS &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id32" id="id13"&gt;[11]&lt;/a&gt; adapter for Qooxdoo, but at the framework side it didn’t gain traction, except
that Martin confirmed importance of the topic, and that also it’s the topic of his master thesis &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id33" id="id14"&gt;[12]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to summarise this section quoting Martin’s &lt;em&gt;focus on our strengths&lt;/em&gt;. How the whole thing looks to me
now, is that in area of website development Qooxdoo team tries to avoid its strengths at all costs. No build
tools, no view model, no application design having great tools, data layer and application design experience.
Instead Qooxdoo team is toying a&amp;nbsp;jQuery/jQueryUI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="a-qooxdoo-website-today"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Qooxdoo website&amp;nbsp;today&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though initial changes in Next doesn’t seem anything promising, I’m interested what the experiment may
yield. But to address the need of a robust development environment for a website today I want to point again
to the bug #7481 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id27" id="id15"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; and its proof of concept project &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id34" id="id16"&gt;[13]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually all blocking bugs for #7481 were resolved and a Qooxdoo native application &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id35" id="id17"&gt;[14]&lt;/a&gt; since 3.5.1 was
already fine as a basis for a website codebase. From my side I’ve been experimenting with the approach on a
few real websites and result are good. When all website’s JavaScript code is centralised, it really starts to
feel like an application, thusly significantly improving maintainability. Late autumn 2014 I’ve written
documentation for the project, backported minor improvements and made it&amp;nbsp;standalone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;qooxdoo-website-skeleton &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id34" id="id18"&gt;[13]&lt;/a&gt; is a mixture of a tutorial and skeleton. Because initial configuration is
tricky, when starting from a scratch with native application, it’s easier to fork and remove a few unused
files. Here I would like to tell about two aspects that Andreas pointed to (see above), and for the rest
you can follow the link. First, a website approach to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UI&lt;/span&gt; here is to provide a choice. One can use qxWeb
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOM&lt;/span&gt; patching facilities or qxWeb widgets. One can use KnockoutJS adapter and use Qooxdoo data models as
view models (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MVVM&lt;/span&gt;). There’s also no restriction for using jQuery or KnockoutJS as is or whatever it makes
sense to&amp;nbsp;use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, is being lightweight. Without external libraries Qooxdoo native application build with basic qxWeb
modules is over 100 kB gzipped. For example boot part for the project is 361/110 kB (optimised/&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;gzip &lt;span class="pre"&gt;-6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;).
I would agree it is a little too much for a website yesterday, but today I don’t see this concern reasonable.
Here are three hello pages for popular social websites requested from desktop&amp;nbsp;Firefox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="43%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="29%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="29%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;website&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;size, kB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;requests&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;twitter.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;156&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;linkedin.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;180&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;facebook.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;615&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here are home pages for big e-commerce&amp;nbsp;websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table border="1" class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;
&lt;col width="41%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="30%" /&gt;
&lt;col width="30%" /&gt;
&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;thead valign="bottom"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th class="head"&gt;website&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;size, kB&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th class="head"&gt;requests&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;ebay.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;alibaba.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;143&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;amazon.com&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;560&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These show that having roughly over 100 kB is a norm today. And if further optimisation of Next will go as
feature-size trade-off, then it wouldn’t probably make&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="epilogue"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before official announcement Next’s bug #8618 was in line with other dubious decisions taken since Qooxdoo
3.5. Before 3.5 I could agree to virtually every decision taken by the team, as there was clear reason,
argument and pragmatic approach&amp;nbsp;overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s mixed. There’s still fundamental work like migration to pointer events, but also several other topics
that look like a waste of time. Like what? Like rewriting the generator to NodeJS and GruntJS &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id36" id="id19"&gt;[15]&lt;/a&gt;.
Surprise! There’s ongoing shift to gulp.js and GruntJS is no longer cool JavaScript thiggie. And I’m curious
to see how Qooxdoo team will handle such situations in general. Fancy toys change in the public sandbox fast
&lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id38" id="id20"&gt;[17]&lt;/a&gt;. Will you try to catch up every new cool replacement or will maintain an unpopular&amp;nbsp;one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like, unconditional &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RESOLVED&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NEVER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="#id37" id="id21"&gt;[16]&lt;/a&gt; set to all old bug. No prioritization, there is no past, the future&amp;#8217;s
so bright. The team briefly state something about turning to an agile development, and happily turned to
developing new features. And of course, no doubt developing features is fun, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PR&lt;/span&gt; is easier with less open
bugs, and resources are always limited. But when new developers stumble the same bugs again and re-report
them, it is a failure. I don’t really understand it, so since that change I’m just discouraged to file new
bug and I don’t. If no one fixes them, and it takes time to analyse, make it reproducible and propose a
solution, I probably shouldn&amp;#8217;t,&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can whine more, but I want to point to two origins of priorities. It’s understanding the scope and
understanding the users. First, is &lt;em&gt;a universal JavaScript framework&lt;/em&gt;. How universal? And what is JavaScript
here? JavaScript like in Netscape? Or like ECMAScript in NodeJS? Should we expect Qooxdoo approach to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt;
routing or database connection pooling? In second, I see opposite sides. One commenters in various places
complain that Qooxdoo &lt;em&gt;doesn’t play well with JavaScript ecosystem&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t think they are Qooxdoo users at
all, but ones who couldn&amp;#8217;t handle it. You know, you can’t do your Qooxdoo work copy-pasting from
StackOverflow, you can do jQuery work this way. On the other side are users, including me, who&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Dear Qooxdoo, we don’t really give a damn about JavaScript ecosystem, you are our only concern. We come
from various established application development platforms, in sense “Swing/qt/Cocoa for the web”.  We
value design and maintainability. Please, keep on avoiding us from it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is to say. I’m an optimist, and there’s nothing parallel to Qooxdoo. So I hope the team won’t forget its
strengths and its users, and will keep on the path of solving real&amp;nbsp;problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id22" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8618"&gt;http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8618&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id23" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slideshare.net/fjakobs/masterin-large-scale-java-script-applications"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/fjakobs/masterin-large-scale-java-script-applications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id24" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;[3]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id3"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id5"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.qooxdoo.org/website-fundamentals-next-challenges"&gt;http://news.qooxdoo.org/website-fundamentals-next-challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id25" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/qooxdoo/next"&gt;http://github.com/qooxdoo/next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id26" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id6"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.qooxdoo.org/qooxdoo-2-0-released"&gt;http://news.qooxdoo.org/qooxdoo-2-0-released&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id27" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;[6]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id7"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id15"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=7481"&gt;http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=7481&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id28" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id9"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://demo.qooxdoo.org/2.0.4/apiviewer/#qx.bom.Collection"&gt;http://demo.qooxdoo.org/2.0.4/apiviewer/#qx.bom.Collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id29" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id10"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.qooxdoo.org/qooxdoo-3-5-released"&gt;http://news.qooxdoo.org/qooxdoo-3-5-released&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id30" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id11"&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_View_ViewModel"&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model_View_ViewModel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id31" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id12"&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8101"&gt;http://bugzilla.qooxdoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8101&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id32" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id13"&gt;[11]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://knockoutjs.com/"&gt;http://knockoutjs.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id33" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id14"&gt;[12]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slideshare.net/wittemann/data-binding-in-qooxdoo"&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/wittemann/data-binding-in-qooxdoo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id34" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;[13]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id16"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id18"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bitbucket.org/saaj/qooxdoo-website-skeleton"&gt;https://bitbucket.org/saaj/qooxdoo-website-skeleton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id35" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;[14]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id8"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id17"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://manual.qooxdoo.org/3.5.1/pages/development/skeletons.html#native"&gt;http://manual.qooxdoo.org/3.5.1/pages/development/skeletons.html#native&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id36" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id19"&gt;[15]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.qooxdoo.org/tool-chain-the-next-step"&gt;http://news.qooxdoo.org/tool-chain-the-next-step&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id37" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id21"&gt;[16]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.eclipsezone.com/eclipse/forums/t83053.html"&gt;http://www.eclipsezone.com/eclipse/forums/t83053.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id38" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label" /&gt;&lt;col /&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="#id20"&gt;[17]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://readwrite.com/2014/12/04/node-js-fork-io-js"&gt;http://readwrite.com/2014/12/04/node-js-fork-io-js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="qooxdoo"></category><category term="javascript"></category><category term="future"></category></entry></feed>